Preliminary Guide to the Mount Vernon Seminary and College Faculty Records, 1950-1999 MVC0039.RG
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Mount Vernon Seminary and College Faculty Records
1950-1999
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MVC0039.RG
5 Linear Feet 9 document boxes, 2 slim document boxes
The Mount Vernon Seminary was officially established by Elizabeth Somers in 1875 and a two year junior college was added in 1927. The Junior College remained open until 1969, when Mount Vernon College became a four-year unversity. The university was an independent institution until 1999, when it became affilated with The George Washington University. This collection includes Mount Vernon Seminary and College faculty records including: faculty meeting minutes, faculty and staff handboks, faculty and staff directories, and faculty correspondence and personal files.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains faculty records from Mount Vernon Seminary and Mount Vernon College, including meeting minutes, handbook, directories, correspondence, and personal files. The material dates from 1890-1998.
Arrangement
Organized into 4 series: Meeting minutes, Handbooks, Directories, and Files and correspondence.
Biographical / Historical
The Mount Vernon Seminary was officially established by Elizabeth Somers in 1875 with classes held at her residence on F Street; she named it after her brother's church in Baltimore, Mount Vernon Place Methodist. The Seminary began as a six year prepatory school, with four years of high school level classes, and two years of post-high school curriculum, calling it a "Family and Day School for Young Ladies." In order to graduate, students had to complete a formal process of "Senior Essays" in which they completed primary research and wrote on a current political or social topic, including such provocative issues as child labor, prohibition, poverty, and women's suffrage.
The school was moved to 1100 M. Street N.W. in 1900 and was once again moved in 1917 to a campus on Nebraska Avenue. In 1920 graduating class, eight women continued their education at universities such as the University of Wisconsin, Stanford, Northwestern and the University of Texas; by 1923 graduates were going to such other prestigious universities as UC-Berkeley, Columbia, Cornell, Smith College and the University of Chicago. Such advancements in higher education were uncommon for women of the day, but Mount Vernon was one of the premier prepatory institutions in the country.
In 1927, Mount Vernon established a Junior College, and with its establishment, students no longer had to complete six years of courses to receive a diploma; they graduated from the Seminary after four years and could continue on to the Junior College for two more years of college preparation. After World War II began, the U.S. Navy took over the campus in 1942 as a part of the war effort. During the 1943 academic year, the Seminary held classes in Spring Valley by leasing neighborhood residences. After receiving "just compensation" for their Nebraska Avneue campus, the school purchased 21 acres on Foxhall Road and surrounding areas in 1945, and had applied for accreditation to award Associates of Arts Degrees after completing two years of the Junior College.
Despite its expansion, by 1965 the Board of Trustees voted unanimously to dissolve the Seminary by 1969, as it could not financially support both institutions. During the 1960s, the Junior College developed new academic concentrations such as government, international relations and political science to reflect its location in the nation's capital. At the same time, it began to phase out its vocational training such as home economics and secretarial skills to make room for these higher education courses.
By 1973, the Board of Higher Education licensed the college to award Bachelor of Arts (BA) degrees such as Public Affairs, Government, Business Administration, Childhood, Special Education, and the Visual Arts, as well as honorary Doctor of Humane Letters and Juris Doctor Degrees; in 1976, the college received initial accreditation as a four-year college and was reaccredited ten years later. However, by 1996 the college announced a plan to affiliate with George Washington University and the last class of Mount Vernon College graduated in 1999. Today, as an affiliated campus of GWU, Mount Vernon offers special living accommodations, as well as learning and leadership programs for female students.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Mount Vernon Seminary and College archives were acquired by GWU upon merger with Mount Vernon College. The collection was transferred to the Foggy Bottom campus in 2009.
Faculty; Women's colleges; Women -- Education; Mount Vernon College; Mount Vernon Seminary
- Meeting minutes, 1950-1998; Series 1; 2 Linear Feet 4 document boxes
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  The materials of this series include minutes from meetings of the Mount Vernon Seminary and College Faculty. They range in date from 1950 to 1998. Included in these meeting minutes include various information including but not limited to: honor roll lists, academic recommendations for specific students, academic policies, proposals for new courses, records of faculty votes on school issues, reminders about upcoming events, reports by faculty committees, administrative reports, etc.
  Women -- Education; Women's colleges; Faculty; Mount Vernon College; Mount Vernon Seminary
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1950-March 1951; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes, April 1951- June 1951; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1954-1956; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1955-1957; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1956-1957; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1959-1960; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1962-1963; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1963-1964; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1964; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1965; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1966; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1966; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1967; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1967-1968; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1968-1969; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1969-1970; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1971-1973; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1989-1991; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1992-1995; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1996; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1997-1998; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Handbooks, 1962-1997; Series 2; 2.25 Linear Feet 4 document boxes, 1 slim document box
  The materials of this series include handbooks for the faculty of Mount Vernon Seminary, Junior College, and College. They range in date from 1962-1997. The handbooks include various information including but not limited to: educational policies and procedures, information on the organization of the faculty, faculty retirement program and other benefits, phone lists, responsibilites of instructors, history of the school, and lists of faculty committees.
  When possible, two copies of each handbook are included.
  Women -- Education; Women's colleges; Faculty; Mount Vernon Seminary; Mount Vernon College
  - MVC Faculty Handbook, 1962-1963; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - MVC Faculty Handbook, 1964-1965; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - MVJC Faculty Handbook, 1967-1968; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - MV Seminary Faculty Handbook, 1968-1969; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - MVC Faculty Handbook, 1972-1973; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - MVC Faculty Handbook, 1974-1975; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - MVC Faculty Handbook, 1975-1976; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - MVC Faculty Handbook, 1976-1977; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - MVC Faculty Handbook, 1977-1978; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - MVC Faculty Handbook, 1978-1979; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - MVC Faculty Handbook, 1979-1980; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - MVC Faculty Handbook, 1980-1981; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - MVC Faculty Handbook, 1981-1982; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - MVC Faculty Handbook, 1982-1983; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - MVC Faculty Handbook, 1983-1984; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - MVC Faculty Handbook, 1984-1985; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - MVC Faculty Handbook, 1985-1986; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - MVC Faculty Handbook, 1986-1987; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - MVC Faculty Handbook, 1987-1988; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - MVC Faculty Handbook, 1988-1989; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - MVC Faculty Handbook, 1992-1993; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - MVC Faculty Handbook, 1995-1996; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - MVC Faculty Handbook, 1995-1996; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - MVC Faculty Handbook, 1996-1997; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - MVC Faculty Handbook, undated; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Directories, 1986-1998; Series 3; 0.5 Linear Feet 1 document box
  The materials of this series include faculty and campus directories from Mount Vernon College. They range in date from 1986-1998. The directories include faculty and staff names, home phone numbers, addresses and positions.
  When possible, two copies of each directory are included.
  Women's colleges; Faculty; Women -- Education; Mount Vernon College; Mount Vernon Seminary
  - MVC Faculty/Staff Directories, 1986-1987; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - MVC Campus Directories, 1995-1997; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - MVC Campus Directories, 1997-1998; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - MVC Faculty Directories, undated; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Files and correspondence, 1938-1999; Series 4; 1.25 Linear Feet 1 document box, 1 slim document box
  The materials of this series include faculty correspondence, committee memos, questionnaires, publications, faculty lists and individual faculty biographical records. They range in date from 1938-1999.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Faculty; Women -- Education; Women's colleges; Mount Vernon Seminary; Mount Vernon College
  - Bevilaqua-Horvath, Lawrence, 1947-1949; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Burke Knapp, Hilary - Theater, 1944-1947; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Carroll, Maria, 1959-1983; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Committee Memos, 1967-1972; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Griffith, Janet C. - Prep English and History, 1956; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Hallowell, Murial B. - Director of Household, 1948-1950; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Hannon, Helen - House Resident, 1945-1954; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Hardin, Fostine Cooper - House Resident, 1953-1956; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Hastings, Helen - correspondence since illness, 1949-1950; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Hendrix, Patricia, 1952; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Henn, Rosaling - Prep School, 1952-1953; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Hubbell, Dorothy - House Resident, 1951-1952; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Jenney, Mrs. Larry L. - English Dept. Prep School, 1955-1956; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Jones, Elizabeth - House Resident, 1949-1956; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Kested, Molly - P.E., 1945-1946; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Kinard, Margaret - Latin Prep School, 1950-1954; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Lamb, Susan - Physical Education, 1951-1953; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Lancaster, Georgina - Science, 1953-1954; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - LaShelle, Ingovar Leighton - Home Economics, 1950-1956; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Lee, Mrs. Charles W. - House Mother, 1960-1961; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - Lester, Anne - Prep School Mathematics, 1954-1956; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 25)
  - Lists/Records, 1938-1970; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - Llewellyn, Phoebe - Dietician, 1946-1947; Series 4 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Mangin, Pauline - Assistant Librarian, 1950; Series 4 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - MacHale, Virginia - Secretary to Registrar, 1948-1950; Series 4 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - McGuffey, Anne - Voice, 1946-1948; Series 4 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Mead, Robert, 1951-1956; Series 4 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Miller, Jean E. - Prep School, 1956; Series 4 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Mills, Sheila - Physical Education, 1953-1954; Series 4 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Mission Questionnaire, undated; Series 4 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Morenus, Gay - Prep School, 1947-1950; Series 4 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Morey, Anne Hefflon - House Resident, 1954; Series 4 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Munn, Marguerite - Art Department, 1939-1949; Series 4 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - November Correspondence, 1976; Series 4 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Publications, 1972-1999; Series 4 (Box 11, Folder 13)